I'd like to introduce you to my mom.
أود أن أعرّفكم على أمي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I'm guessing that's not what you expected,
أعتقد أن هذا ما لم تتوقعوه،
and it's not what I expected either,
وما لم أتوقعه أيضًا،
and thank goodness I realized that an Asian man was not my mom
وحمدًا لله أني أدركت أن الرجل الآسيوي لم يكن أمي
before I hugged him,
قبل أن أعانقه،
because that would have been so awkward.
لأن هذا كان سيبدو محرجًا جدًا.
Recognizing people isn't one of my strengths
التعرف على الناس لم يكن أحد نقاط قوتي
due to a genetic visual impairment that has no correction or cure.
ويعزو ذلك إلى إعاقة بصرية وراثية والتي لا يوجد لها تصحيح أو علاج.
As a result, I am legally blind,
ونتيجة لذلك، فأنا عمياء قانونًا،
though I prefer "partially sighted" because it's more optimistic.
وبرغم ذلك أفضل وصف "ضعيفة النظر" لأنه أكثر تفاؤلًا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I'm entitled to the label "disabled."
وصنفت تحت مسمى "معاقة."
I hate the word disabled when it's used to describe people.
أكره كلمة معاق عند أستخدمها لوصف الناس.
It detonates a mindset of less than
لأنها تدل على عقلية متدنية
that utterly disregards capacity,
عن تلك التي تستخف تمامًا بمبدأ الاستطاعة،
ability, potential,
والقدرة والإمكانية،
instead prioritizing brokenness
بدلًا من ذلك تعطي الأولوية لحالة التحطم
and lack.
والحرمان.
The perspective can be overt.
وجهة النظر هذه قد تكون صريحة.
What can't he do for himself that I'm going to have to do for him?
فما الذي لا يستطيع أن يفعله وبإمكاني أنا أن أقوم به؟
She'll probably need some accommodation
ربما ستحتاج بعض التكيّف
that no other employee at this business needs.
الذي لا يحتاجه الموظفون في هذا المجال.
Sometimes, the hidden bias
في بعض الأحيان، يكون التحيّز الخفي
is so sweetly conveyed.
ظاهرًا بشكل لطيف.
"Wow, Susan,
"عجبًا يا سوزان،
look at everything you've done in your career and your life.
انظري إلى كل ما حققتيه في مسيرتك المهنية وحياتك.
How did you do all of that and be visually impaired?"
كيف حققتي كل ذلك رغم إعاقتك البصرية؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I fail at being disabled.
فشلت في أن أكون معاقة.
So in the spirit of incentivizing the rampant failure
لذا في ظل روح التحفيز للفشل المنتشرة
of people all over the world
في الناس حول العالم
and enticing the so-called normal to just give it a rest already,
وجذب الأسوياء المزعومين للتوقف عن التكلم عن الإعاقة الفعلية،
here are five tips
إليكم خمسة نصائح
to fail at being disabled.
لتفشلوا في أن تكونوا معاقين.
Tip one:
النصيحة الأولى:
know your superpowers.
اعرف نقاط قوتك الخارقة.
The best team I ever led in my career
أعظم فريق توليت قيادته في مسيرتي المهنية
was based on superpowers,
كان معتمدًا على نقاط القوة الخارقة،
and we even gave ourselves fancy-pantsy titles
لدرجة أننا أعطينا لأنفسنا ألقابًا مذهلة
like "the Pillar of Masterly Acumen."
مثل "أساس الفطنة البارع."
"The Biscuit Butterer."
و"داهن البسكويت بالزبد."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"The Voice of Reason."
و"صوت الحكمة"
Because we relied on our strengths,
لأننا اعتمدنا على نقاط قوتنا،
our best strengths,
أفضل نقاط قوتنا،
we achieved tremendous outcomes.
وقد حققنا نتائج مذهلة.
The trait that prevents me from recognizing my mom
إن الخاصية التي جعلتني لا أتعرف على أمي
allows me to smoothly adapt,
سمحت لي بالتكيف بكل سلاسة،
to quickly absorb and accurately process an exhausting volume of cues,
للاستيعاب سريعًا والعمل بدقة على حجم هائل من الدلائل،
tease out what's important,
واستخلاص ما يمثل أهمية،
determine multiple processes or potentials for any situation that I'm in,
وتحديد الإجراءات أو الإمكانيات المتعددة لأي موقف أتعرض له.
and then select the one that makes the most sense,
ثم أختار ما هو مناسب،
all in a matter of seconds.
كل ذلك في غضون ثوان.
I see what other people do not.
أرى ما لا يراه الناس الآخرون.
Some people think that's a superpower,
يظن بعض الناس أن هذه قوة خارقة،
but my real superpowers
لكن قواي الخارقة الحقيقية
are ricocheting off of glass walls --
هو الارتداد عن الحوائط الزجاجية،
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
and letting my friends walk around with kale in their teeth.
وترك أصدقائي يمشون ببقايا من اللفت في أسنانهم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's true. Don't have lunch with me,
هذا حقيقي، لاتتناولوا الغداء معي،
or dinner.
أو العشاء.
Tip two: be supremely skilled,
الخطوة الثانية: كن صاحب مهارات عالية،
supremely skilled at getting it wrong.
صاحب مهارات عالية في الفهم الخاطئ.
It is important to be as equally confident in your superpowers
فمن المهم أن تكون واثقًا في قواك الخارقة
as you are in you FUBARs.
بنفس قدر ثقتك في (فيوبار).
That's "effed up beyond all recognition"
وهي اختصار: "تبًا لدرجة تفوق التصور"
for you millennials.
لك يا جيل الألفية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Here's a good example.
إليكم مثالًا جيدًا.
It is not a great idea to say,
ليست فكرة سديدة أن تقول:
"Don't worry, everything in here is too small for me to see"
"لاتقلق، كل شيء هنا ضئيل بالنسبة لي كي أراه"
when you accidentally walk into the men's room --
عندما تدخلي بالصدفة غرفة الرجال،
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
at one of the world's largest sporting arenas --
في إحدى أكبر الصالات الرياضية العالمية،
or anywhere.
أو في أي مكان آخر.
I really wish that one wasn't true.
أتمنى حقًا أن تلك المرة لم تكن حقيقية.
I'm serious. It is better to just walk out and let them think you're drunk.
أنا جادة، فمن الأفضل أن تخرجي وتدعيهم يظنون أنك ثملة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Tip three: know that everyone is disabled in some way,
النصيحة الثالثة: اعلم أن الجميع معاق بطريقة ما.
like when you have a cold and you can't smell
مثلما تكون مصابًا بالبرد ولا تستطيع الشم
and you realize that the milk that you splashed in your coffee was sour
وتدرك أن اللبن الذي وضعته في قهوتك كان حامضًا
only after you've tasted it.
وذلك بعد أن تذوقتها.
Very recently, a woman walked up to me frantic.
في الآونة الأخيرة، أتت امرأة ثائرة إلي.
She could not find the bakery she was looking for.
لم تستطع إيجاد المخبز التي كانت تبحث عنه.
As I motioned in the direction I thought she should go,
وأنا أشير إلى الجهة التي أعتقد أن عليها الذهاب إليها،
saying, "There are no stores on this side of the street
قائلةً: "لاتوجد متاجر في هذا الجانب من الشارع
so your best bet is to cross --"
لذا فأفضل خيار هو أن تعبري..."
"Oh my goodness," she interrupted.
"حمدًا لله،" قاطعتني.
"There it is.
"ها هو.
All I needed was another set of eyes."
كل ما أحتاجه هو عينان إضافيتان."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I just let her have it.
سمحت لها ببساطة أن تحصل عليهما.
I would have said that, you know,
كنت لأقول، تعرفون،
being logical and paying attention
أن تكون عقلانيًا وأن تولي الانتباه
and staying calm would have done the trick,
وأن تبقى هادئًأ كان هذا سيحبك الخدعة،
but who am I?
لكن من أنا؟
Tip four: point out the disability in others.
النصيحة الرابعة: حدد إعاقة الآخرين.
This one is best reserved -- very important note --
تلك الخطوة محفوظة، وهي ملحوظة مهمة جدًا،
this one is best reserved for people you know well,
تلك النصيحة محفوظة للناس الذين تعرفهم جيدًا.
because random strangers typically don't appreciate
لأن الغرباء العابرين عادة لا يُقدّرون
teachable moments.
اللحظات التعليمية.
A few years ago, my parents and I went to see the Rockettes,
قبل عدة سنوات، ذهبت أنا ووالدايّ لمشاهدة (الروكتس)،
Radio City's high-kicking dancers.
راقصات الركل العالي في قاعة راديو سيتي.
I leaned over to my dad.
ملت نحو والدي.
"The two Rockettes on the left aren't kicking in a straight line."
"راقصتي الروكتس ناحية اليسار لا تركلان في خط مستقيم."
"Yes, they are."
"بلى، إنهما تفعلان."
"No, they're not."
لا، هما ليستا كذلك."
"Yes, they are, and how do you know?
"بلى، هما تفعلان، وكيف تعرفين ذلك؟
You can't see."
لا يمكنك الرؤية."
But I know what a straight line looks like.
لكني أعرف كيف يبدو الخط المستقيم.
I had snapped a picture during our back and forth
لقد التقطت صورة خلال ذهابنا وعودتنا
and presented him the evidence that proved I was right.
وقدمت له الدليل أني كنت مُحقة.
He looked at the picture.
نظر إلى الصورة.
I leaned in further.
وملت إلى الأمام أكثر.
"Who's disabled now?"
"مَن المعاق الآن؟"
Tip five: pursue audacious goals.
النصيحة الخامسة: اسع وراء أهداف جريئة.
Flip expectation upside down
اقلب التوقعات رأسًا على عقب
and shove limitation off a cliff to meet its demise.
وارمِ القيود من أعلى جرف لتلقى حتفها.
There is a college football linebacker
هناك لاعب ظهير لكرة قدم الجامعات
who blitzes, tackles, recovers fumbles
يقطع الهجمات ويتصدى للكرة ويستعيد السيطرة
while having one hand.
في حين أن لديه يد واحدة.
There is a teacher who successfully transfers knowledge
هناك معلم ناجح جدًا في توصيل المعرفة
and inspires countless students
وإلهام عدد لا يحصى من الطلاب
while living with Down syndrome.
وهو يعاني من متلازمة (داون).
And for me,
وبالنسبة لي،
on my long list,
على قائمتي الطويلة،
to cycle from Kathmandu, Nepal, to Darjeeling, India
أن أركب الدراجة من (كاتمندو) في (نيبال) إلى (دارجلينغ) في (الهند)
on the backseat of a bicycle built for two.
في المقعد الخلفي لدراجة مصممة لشخصين.
It will be an exciting 620-mile adventure,
ستكون مغامرة مثيرة طولها 620 ميلًا،
and I'm sure I will have the blurry photos to show for it.
وأنا موقنة أني سأحصل على صور ضبابية لأفتخر بها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Oh, before we go on, I forgot to introduce you to my mom.
أوه، قبل أن نواصل، نسيت أن أعرفكم بأمي.
I need to do that.
أنا بحاجة لفعل ذلك.
And here she is,
وها هي،
as she would appear to me
كما تبدو لي
if I were looking through a crowd of people looking for her.
إذا كنت أنظر في حشد من الناس بحثًا عنها.
Or is that an Asian man?
أو أن هذا رجلًا أسيويًا؟
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)